so let's discuss can compilers help
improve IPC which is the number of
instructions per cycle that the
processor achieves
there are really two things that the
compiler can help with one is the ILP of
the program itself may be limited for
example due to dependence chains which
is when we have instructions that depend
on each other so really if we have a
long chain like this then there would be
very limited ILP in this program because
we can really execute only one
instruction at a time so the compiler as
we will see might help us actually avoid
these kinds of dependent chains and also
the hardware has a limited window into
the program for example there might be
independent instructions so an ideal
processor might be able to achieve good
ILP on that program but because these
independent instructions are far apart a
real processor simply cannot see those
instructions because for example it runs
out of Rob space before it reaches those
instructions that are independent so in
the same example if we have a long chain
like this followed by
this instruction doesn't depend on any
of those in the chain but if the chain
is too long we run out of Arabic space
before we reach this instruction so as
far as this processor is concerned this
instruction cannot execute in parallel
with those just because we never see it
as we will see the compiler can help us
put this independent instructions closer
to each other so that the IPC achieved
by the processor is closer to the
available ILP